<!DOCTYPE html>
<html><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0"><channel><title>LCOW - Stefan Scherer's Blog</title><description>Just my techie notes.</description><link>http://localhost:2368/</link><image><url>http://localhost:2368/favicon.png</url><title>LCOW - Stefan Scherer's Blog</title><link>http://localhost:2368/</link></image><generator>Ghost 1.8</generator><lastBuildDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2018 18:06:22 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:2368/tag/lcow/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title>A sneak peek at LCOW</title><description>&lt;div class="kg-card-markdown"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last week a major &lt;a href="https://github.com/moby/moby/pull/34859"&gt;pull request&lt;/a&gt; to support Linux Containers on Windows (LCOW) has landed in master branch of the Docker project. With that feature enabled you will be able to run &lt;strong&gt;both Linux and Windows containers side-by-side&lt;/strong&gt; with a single Docker engine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So let's have a look how a&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/sneak-peek-at-lcow/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5a64a75ee5611a0001acf91f</guid><category>Docker</category><category>LCOW</category><category>Linux</category><category>Windows 10</category><dc:creator>Stefan Scherer</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2018 15:30:58 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;div class="kg-card-markdown"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last week a major &lt;a href="https://github.com/moby/moby/pull/34859"&gt;pull request&lt;/a&gt; to support Linux Containers on Windows (LCOW) has landed in master branch of the Docker project. With that feature enabled you will be able to run &lt;strong&gt;both Linux and Windows containers side-by-side&lt;/strong&gt; with a single Docker engine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So let's have a look how a Windows 10 developer machine will look like in near future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2018/01/lcow.png" alt="LCOW on Windows 10"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Docker command &lt;code&gt;docker ps&lt;/code&gt; lists all your running Linux and Windows containers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can use volumes to share data between containers and the host.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The containers can talk to each other over the container networks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can publish ports to your host and use localhost. But wait, this is still a Windows Insider feature coming to Windows 10 1803 release.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="runninglinuxcontainers"&gt;Running Linux containers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the moment you need to specify the &lt;code&gt;--platform&lt;/code&gt; option to pull Linux images. This option is also needed when the specific Docker images is a multi-arch image for both Linux and Windows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;docker pull --platform linux alpine
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you have pulled Linux images you can run them without the &lt;code&gt;--platform&lt;/code&gt; option.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;docker run alpine uname -a
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To allow Windows run Linux containers a small Hyper-V VM is needed. The LinuxKit project provides an image for LCOW at &lt;a href="https://github.com/linuxkit/lcow"&gt;https://github.com/linuxkit/lcow&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="sharedvolumes"&gt;Shared volumes&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's see how containers of different platforms can share data in a simple way. You can bind mount a volume into Linux and Windows containers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2018/01/lcow-in-action.gif" alt="LCOW in action with shared volumes"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following example shares a folder from the host with a Linux and Windows container.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First create a folder on the Windows 10 host:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;cd \
mkdir host
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h3 id="runalinuxcontainer"&gt;Run a Linux container&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the Windows 10 host run a Linux container and bind mount the folder as &lt;code&gt;/test&lt;/code&gt; in the Linux container.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;docker run -it -v C:\host:/test alpine sh
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Linux container create a file in that mounted volume.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;uname -a &amp;gt; test/hello-from-linux.txt
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h3 id="runawindowscontainer"&gt;Run a Windows container&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the Windows 10 host run a Windows container and bind mount the folder as &lt;code&gt;C:\test&lt;/code&gt; in the Windows container.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;docker run -i -v C:\host:C:\test microsoft/nanoserver:1709 cmd
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Windows container create a file in that mounted volume.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;ver &amp;gt; test\hello-from-windows.txt
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h3 id="result"&gt;Result&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the Windows 10 host list the files in the shared folder&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;PS C:\&amp;gt; dir host


    Directory: C:\host


Mode                LastWriteTime         Length Name
----                -------------         ------ ----
-a----        1/21/2018   4:32 AM             85 hello-from-linux.txt
-a----        1/21/2018   4:33 AM             46 hello-from-windows.txt
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is super convenient for development environments to share configuration files or even source code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="buildyourowntestenvironment"&gt;Build your own test environment&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to try LCOW yourself I suggest to spin up a fresh Windows 10 VM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="azure"&gt;Azure&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have tested LCOW with a Windows 10 1709 VM in Azure. Choose a V3 machine to have nested hypervisor which you will need to run Hyper-V containers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="containersandhyperv"&gt;Containers and Hyper-V&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enable the Containers feature and Hyper-V feature:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Enable-WindowsOptionalFeature -Online -FeatureName containers -All -NoRestart
Enable-WindowsOptionalFeature -Online -FeatureName Microsoft-Hyper-V -All -NoRestart
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h3 id="linuxkit"&gt;LinuxKit&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now install the LinuxKit image for LCOW. I have catched the latest from a CircleCI artifact, but soon there will be a new release in the &lt;a href="https://github.com/linuxkit/lcow/releases"&gt;linuxkit/lcow&lt;/a&gt; repo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Invoke-WebRequest -OutFile &amp;quot;$env:TEMP\linuxkit-lcow.zip&amp;quot; &amp;quot;https://23-111085629-gh.circle-artifacts.com/0/release.zip&amp;quot;
Expand-Archive -Path &amp;quot;$env:TEMP\linuxkit-lcow.zip&amp;quot; -DestinationPath &amp;quot;$env:ProgramFiles\Linux Containers&amp;quot; -Force
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h3 id="dockernightlybuild"&gt;Docker nightly build&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now download and install the Docker engine. As this pull request only landed in master branch we have to use the nightly build for now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Invoke-WebRequest -OutFile &amp;quot;$env:TEMP\docker-master.zip&amp;quot; &amp;quot;https://master.dockerproject.com/windows/x86_64/docker.zip&amp;quot;
Expand-Archive -Path &amp;quot;$env:TEMP\docker-master.zip&amp;quot; -DestinationPath $env:ProgramFiles -Force
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next command installs the Docker service and enables the experimental features.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;. $env:ProgramFiles\docker\dockerd.exe --register-service --experimental
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Set the PATH variable to have the Docker CLI available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Environment]::SetEnvironmentVariable(&amp;quot;Path&amp;quot;, $env:Path + &amp;quot;;$($env:ProgramFiles)\docker&amp;quot;, [EnvironmentVariableTarget]::Machine)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now reboot the machine to finish the Containers and Hyper-V installation. After the reboot the Docker engine should be up and running and the Docker CLI can be used from the PowerShell terminal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="localvagrantenvironment"&gt;Local Vagrant environment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have &lt;a href="https://vagrantup.com"&gt;Vagrant&lt;/a&gt; installed with Hyper-V or VMware as your hypervisor, you can spin up a local test environment with a few commands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First clone my GitHub repo &lt;a href="https://github.com/StefanScherer/docker-windows-box"&gt;docker-windows-box&lt;/a&gt; which has a LCOW environment to play with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;git clone https://github.com/StefanScherer/docker-windows-box
cd docker-windows-box
cd lcow
vagrant up
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will download the Vagrant base box if needed, spins up the Windows 10 VM and automatically installs all features shown above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With all these new Docker features coming to Windows in the next few months, Windows 10 is evolving to the most interesting developer platform in 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine what's possible: Use a &lt;code&gt;docker-compose.yml&lt;/code&gt; to spin up a mixed scenario with Linux and Windows containers, live debug your app from Visual Studio Code, and much more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you liked this blog post please share it with your friends. You can follow me on Twitter &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/stefscherer"&gt;@stefscherer&lt;/a&gt; to stay updated with Windows containers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>DockerCon: LCOW and Windows Server 1709</title><description>&lt;div class="kg-card-markdown"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last week was a busy week as a Docker Captain. Many of us came to Copenhagen to DockerCon EU 2017. You may have heard of the surprising news about Kubernetes coming to Docker. But there were also some other new announcements about Windows Containers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="dockeronwindowsworkshop"&gt;Docker on Windows Workshop&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Monday&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/dockercon-lcow-and-windows-server-1709/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">59f3b65cdd4c1b0001e301e7</guid><category>DockerCon</category><category>windows-containers</category><category>LCOW</category><category>Windows Server 1709</category><dc:creator>Stefan Scherer</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 28 Oct 2017 00:18:11 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;div class="kg-card-markdown"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last week was a busy week as a Docker Captain. Many of us came to Copenhagen to DockerCon EU 2017. You may have heard of the surprising news about Kubernetes coming to Docker. But there were also some other new announcements about Windows Containers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="dockeronwindowsworkshop"&gt;Docker on Windows Workshop&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Monday I helped &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/EltonStoneman"&gt;Elton Stoneman&lt;/a&gt; in his Docker on Windows Workshop. This time it was a full-day workshop and it was fully packed with 50 people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2017/10/dowws.jpg" alt="Docker on Windows Workshop"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elton is always running the workshop at a rapic pace, but don't worry the workshop material is all public &lt;a href="https://github.com/sixeyed/docker-windows-workshop"&gt;available on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;. So we went through dockerizing &lt;a href="http://ASP.NET"&gt;ASP.NET&lt;/a&gt; apps, adding Prometheus, Grafana and an ELK stack for monitoring, building a Jenkins CI pipeline and finally running a Docker Swarm. There is lots of things to look up in the material. If you prefer a book, I can recommend his &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.de/Docker-Windows-Elt%E2%80%A6"&gt;Docker on Windows&lt;/a&gt; book which is also fully packed with many tips and tricks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="lcowtheinsidestory"&gt;LCOW - The Inside Story&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my favorite talks was by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/gigastarks"&gt;John Starks&lt;/a&gt; from Microsoft about Linux Container on Windows - The Inside Story. He explained how LinuxKit is used to run a small HyperV VM for the Linux containers to provide the Linux kernel. On his Windows 10 1709 machine he also gave pretty good live demos. The &lt;a href="https://dockercon.docker.com/watch/U7Bxp66uKmemZssjCTyXkm"&gt;video is online&lt;/a&gt; and is worth watching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2017/10/dcon-lcow.jpg" alt="Linux and Windows containers side-by-side"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the photo you can see an alpine and nanoserver container running side-by-side. So you will no longer need to switch between Linux and Windows containers, it just works. He also showed that volumes work between Linux and Windows containers. This demo was done with a special Docker engine as not all pull requests haven't been merged. But still challenging for me to try this on a own machine ...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="windowsserver1709"&gt;Windows Server 1709&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the DockerCon week Microsoft has announced the availability of Windows Server Version 1709 for download. I first looked at the Azure Portal, but found nothing yet. I also couldn't find the downloads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So after the LCOW talk I used a Windows 10 VM in Azure and installed the Fall Creators Update to have 1709 on that desktop machine. I found the missing pull request and compiled a Docker engine from source and then I had my LCOW moment:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2017/10/docker-run-lcow.gif" alt="docker-run-lcow"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you see this the first time working and know what technical details had to be solved make make it look so simple and easy - awesome!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next day I found the Windows Server 1709 ISO in my MSDN subscription. So I could start working on a Packer template in my &lt;a href="https://github.com/StefanScherer/packer-windows"&gt;packer-windows&lt;/a&gt; GitHub repo to automate the creation of such Windows VM's. But DockerCon is to meet people and learn new things: &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/NicholasDille"&gt;Nicholas Dille&lt;/a&gt; went another very interesting way to &lt;a href="http://dille.name/blog/2017/10/25/building-a-windowscontainer-docker-host-without-running-windows-setup/"&gt;build a VM with Docker without running Windows Setup&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="smallerwindowsimages"&gt;Smaller Windows images&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the last months we could follow the progress of the Windows Server in several Insider builds. I blogged about the &lt;a href="https://stefanscherer.github.io/exploring-new-nanoserver-insider-images/"&gt;smaller NanoServer Insider images&lt;/a&gt; in July going down to 80-90 MByte. Now with the new release of Windows Server 1709 and Windows 10 version 1709 we now can use official images.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;microsoft/windowsservercore:1709&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;microsoft/nanoserver:1709&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;microsoft/dotnet:2.0.0-*-nanoserver-1709&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;microsoft/aspnet:4.7.1-windowsservercore-1709&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest discussion is about having no PowerShell in the small nanoserver image. For me it's a nice fit to just &lt;code&gt;COPY&lt;/code&gt; deploy microservices into the Windows image.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven't seen an official PowerShell base image based on nanoserver, but there is at least the beta version&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;microsoft/powershell:6.0.0-beta.9-nanoserver-1709&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also have pushed some images to the Docker Hub to get started with other languages and tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2017/10/Bildschirmfoto-2017-10-19-um-11.14.43.png" alt="Bildschirmfoto-2017-10-19-um-11.14.43"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don't have HyperV installed in Windows Server 1709 (maybe you are running a VM in the Cloud) then you cannot run older Windows Docker image on the new server. All images have to be built based on the new 1709 base images.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Windows 10 users always use HyperV to run Linux or Windows containers, so you don't feel that hard constraint on your developer machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It will be interesting to see how the multiple Windows versions evolve and when the next Insider program is giving us early access to the upcoming features.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="captainshackday"&gt;Captains Hack Day&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On our Docker Captains Hack Day &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/mikesir87"&gt;Michael Irwin&lt;/a&gt; has started a better &lt;a href="https://github.com/mikesir87/swarm-viz"&gt;Swarm Visualizer 2.0&lt;/a&gt;. During the day we have added a first CI pipeline and - of course - Windows support. But not only Windows! With some magic multi-stage multi-arch builds we also managed to cross-build the visualizer on an Intel machine and create a Docker image for IBM z390 mainframes. &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/estesp"&gt;Phil Estes&lt;/a&gt; tested the image in the IBM cloud. I'll write a more detailed blog post about how to cross-build Node.js apps with Docker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2017/10/captain-hack-day.jpg" alt="captain-hack-day"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That was a fascinating week at DockerCon. Thanks to Jenny, Ashlinn, Victor, Mano ... for making this event so wonderful. I had a lot of hallway tracks to talk with many people about Windows Containers in devolpment and production. Share and learn!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stefan&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/stefscherer"&gt;@stefscherer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss></html>