<!DOCTYPE html>
<html><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Linux - Stefan Scherer's Blog</title><description>Just my techie notes.</description><link>http://localhost:2368/</link><image><url>http://localhost:2368/favicon.png</url><title>Linux - Stefan Scherer's Blog</title><link>http://localhost:2368/</link></image><generator>Ghost 1.8</generator><lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 07:15:58 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:2368/tag/linux/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title>A sneak peek at LCOW</title><description>&lt;div class="kg-card-markdown"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last week a major &lt;a href="https://github.com/moby/moby/pull/34859"&gt;pull request&lt;/a&gt; to support Linux Containers on Windows (LCOW) has landed in master branch of the Docker project. With that feature enabled you will be able to run &lt;strong&gt;both Linux and Windows containers side-by-side&lt;/strong&gt; with a single Docker engine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So let's have a look how a&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/sneak-peek-at-lcow/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5a64a75ee5611a0001acf91f</guid><category>Docker</category><category>LCOW</category><category>Linux</category><category>Windows 10</category><dc:creator>Stefan Scherer</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2018 15:30:58 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;div class="kg-card-markdown"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last week a major &lt;a href="https://github.com/moby/moby/pull/34859"&gt;pull request&lt;/a&gt; to support Linux Containers on Windows (LCOW) has landed in master branch of the Docker project. With that feature enabled you will be able to run &lt;strong&gt;both Linux and Windows containers side-by-side&lt;/strong&gt; with a single Docker engine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So let's have a look how a Windows 10 developer machine will look like in near future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2018/01/lcow-marked.jpg" alt="LCOW on Windows 10"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Docker command &lt;code&gt;docker ps&lt;/code&gt; lists all your running Linux and Windows containers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can use volumes to share data between containers and the host.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The containers can talk to each other over the container networks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can publish ports to your host and use localhost. But wait, this is still a Windows Insider feature coming to Windows 10 1803 release.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="runninglinuxcontainers"&gt;Running Linux containers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the moment you need to specify the &lt;code&gt;--platform&lt;/code&gt; option to pull Linux images. This option is also needed when the specific Docker images is a multi-arch image for both Linux and Windows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;docker pull --platform linux alpine
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you have pulled Linux images you can run them without the &lt;code&gt;--platform&lt;/code&gt; option.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;docker run alpine uname -a
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To allow Windows run Linux containers a small Hyper-V VM is needed. The LinuxKit project provides an image for LCOW at &lt;a href="https://github.com/linuxkit/lcow"&gt;https://github.com/linuxkit/lcow&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="sharedvolumes"&gt;Shared volumes&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's see how containers of different platforms can share data in a simple way. You can bind mount a volume into Linux and Windows containers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2018/01/lcow-in-action.gif" alt="LCOW in action with shared volumes"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following example shares a folder from the host with a Linux and Windows container.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First create a folder on the Windows 10 host:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;cd \
mkdir host
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h3 id="runalinuxcontainer"&gt;Run a Linux container&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the Windows 10 host run a Linux container and bind mount the folder as &lt;code&gt;/test&lt;/code&gt; in the Linux container.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;docker run -it -v C:\host:/test alpine sh
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Linux container create a file in that mounted volume.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;uname -a &amp;gt; test/hello-from-linux.txt
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h3 id="runawindowscontainer"&gt;Run a Windows container&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the Windows 10 host run a Windows container and bind mount the folder as &lt;code&gt;C:\test&lt;/code&gt; in the Windows container.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;docker run -i -v C:\host:C:\test microsoft/nanoserver:1709 cmd
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Windows container create a file in that mounted volume.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;ver &amp;gt; test\hello-from-windows.txt
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h3 id="result"&gt;Result&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the Windows 10 host list the files in the shared folder&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;PS C:\&amp;gt; dir host


    Directory: C:\host


Mode                LastWriteTime         Length Name
----                -------------         ------ ----
-a----        1/21/2018   4:32 AM             85 hello-from-linux.txt
-a----        1/21/2018   4:33 AM             46 hello-from-windows.txt
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is super convenient for development environments to share configuration files or even source code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="draftingmixedworkloads"&gt;Drafting mixed workloads&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With Docker Compose you can spin up a mixed container environment. I just did these first steps to spin up a Linux and Windows web server.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-yaml"&gt;version: &amp;quot;3.2&amp;quot;

services:

  web1:
    image: nginx
    volumes:
      - type: bind
        source: C:\host
        target: /test
    ports:
      - 80:80

  web2:
    image: stefanscherer/hello-dresden:0.0.3-windows-1709
    volumes:
      - type: bind
        source: C:\host
        target: C:\test
    ports:
      - 81:3000

networks:
  default:
    external:
      name: nat
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think of a Linux database and a Window front end, or vice versa...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="buildyourownlcowtestenvironment"&gt;Build your own LCOW test environment&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to try LCOW yourself I suggest to spin up a fresh Windows 10 1709 VM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="azure"&gt;Azure&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have tested LCOW with a Windows 10 1709 VM in Azure. Choose a V3 machine to have nested hypervisor which you will need to run Hyper-V containers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="containersandhyperv"&gt;Containers and Hyper-V&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enable the Containers feature and Hyper-V feature:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Enable-WindowsOptionalFeature -Online -FeatureName containers -All -NoRestart
Enable-WindowsOptionalFeature -Online -FeatureName Microsoft-Hyper-V -All -NoRestart
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h3 id="linuxkit"&gt;LinuxKit&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now install the LinuxKit image for LCOW. I have catched the latest from a CircleCI artifact, but soon there will be a new release in the &lt;a href="https://github.com/linuxkit/lcow/releases"&gt;linuxkit/lcow&lt;/a&gt; repo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Invoke-WebRequest -OutFile &amp;quot;$env:TEMP\linuxkit-lcow.zip&amp;quot; &amp;quot;https://23-111085629-gh.circle-artifacts.com/0/release.zip&amp;quot;
Expand-Archive -Path &amp;quot;$env:TEMP\linuxkit-lcow.zip&amp;quot; -DestinationPath &amp;quot;$env:ProgramFiles\Linux Containers&amp;quot; -Force
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h3 id="dockernightlybuild"&gt;Docker nightly build&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now download and install the Docker engine. As this pull request only landed in master branch we have to use the nightly build for now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Invoke-WebRequest -OutFile &amp;quot;$env:TEMP\docker-master.zip&amp;quot; &amp;quot;https://master.dockerproject.com/windows/x86_64/docker.zip&amp;quot;
Expand-Archive -Path &amp;quot;$env:TEMP\docker-master.zip&amp;quot; -DestinationPath $env:ProgramFiles -Force
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next command installs the Docker service and enables the experimental features.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;. $env:ProgramFiles\docker\dockerd.exe --register-service --experimental
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Set the PATH variable to have the Docker CLI available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Environment]::SetEnvironmentVariable(&amp;quot;Path&amp;quot;, $env:Path + &amp;quot;;$($env:ProgramFiles)\docker&amp;quot;, [EnvironmentVariableTarget]::Machine)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now reboot the machine to finish the Containers and Hyper-V installation. After the reboot the Docker engine should be up and running and the Docker CLI can be used from the PowerShell terminal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="localvagrantenvironment"&gt;Local Vagrant environment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have &lt;a href="https://vagrantup.com"&gt;Vagrant&lt;/a&gt; installed with Hyper-V or VMware as your hypervisor, you can spin up a local test environment with a few commands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First clone my GitHub repo &lt;a href="https://github.com/StefanScherer/docker-windows-box"&gt;docker-windows-box&lt;/a&gt; which has a LCOW environment to play with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;git clone https://github.com/StefanScherer/docker-windows-box
cd docker-windows-box
cd lcow
vagrant up
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will download the Vagrant base box if needed, spins up the Windows 10 VM and automatically installs all features shown above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With all these new Docker features coming to Windows in the next few months, Windows 10 is evolving to the most interesting developer platform in 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine what's possible: Use a &lt;code&gt;docker-compose.yml&lt;/code&gt; to spin up a mixed scenario with Linux and Windows containers, live debug your app from Visual Studio Code, and much more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you liked this blog post please share it with your friends. You can follow me on Twitter &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/stefscherer"&gt;@stefscherer&lt;/a&gt; to stay updated with Windows containers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Run Linux and Windows Containers on Windows 10</title><description>&lt;div class="kg-card-markdown"&gt;&lt;p&gt;At DockerCon 2016 in Seattle Docker announced the public beta of &lt;strong&gt;Docker for Windows&lt;/strong&gt;. With this you can work with Docker running &lt;strong&gt;Linux containers&lt;/strong&gt; in a very easy way on Windows 10 Pro with Hyper-V installed. In the meantime there is a &lt;a href="https://docs.docker.com/docker-for-windows/"&gt;stable version and a beta channel&lt;/a&gt; to retrieve&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/run-linux-and-windows-containers-on-windows-10/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5986d4ec688a490001540968</guid><category>Docker</category><category>Windows</category><category>Linux</category><dc:creator>Stefan Scherer</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 24 Sep 2016 12:55:29 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;div class="kg-card-markdown"&gt;&lt;p&gt;At DockerCon 2016 in Seattle Docker announced the public beta of &lt;strong&gt;Docker for Windows&lt;/strong&gt;. With this you can work with Docker running &lt;strong&gt;Linux containers&lt;/strong&gt; in a very easy way on Windows 10 Pro with Hyper-V installed. In the meantime there is a &lt;a href="https://docs.docker.com/docker-for-windows/"&gt;stable version and a beta channel&lt;/a&gt; to retrieve newer versions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And Microsoft has added the &lt;strong&gt;Containers feature&lt;/strong&gt; in the Windows 10 Anniversary Update. With some &lt;a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/virtualization/windowscontainers/quick_start/quick_start_windows_10"&gt;installation steps&lt;/a&gt; you are able to run &lt;strong&gt;Windows Hyper-V Containers&lt;/strong&gt; on your Windows 10 machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there is a little bit of confusion which sort of containers can be started with each of the two installations. And you can't run both Docker Engines side-by-side without some adjustments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is because each of the installations use the same default named pipe &lt;code&gt;//./pipe/docker_engine&lt;/code&gt; causing one of the engines to fail to start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="beta26torulethemall"&gt;Beta 26 to rule them all&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beginning with the Docker for Windows Beta 26 there is a very easy approach to solve this confusion. You only have to install Docker for Windows with the MSI installer. There is a new menu item in the Docker tray icon to switch between Linux and Windows containers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2016/09/docker-for-windows-switch.gif" alt="switching"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see in the video you don't have to change environment variables or use the &lt;code&gt;-H&lt;/code&gt; option of the Docker client to talk to the other Docker engine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if you download &lt;a href="https://docs.docker.com/docker-for-windows/"&gt;Docker for Windows beta&lt;/a&gt; or switch to the beta channel in your installation you can try this out yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The installer will activate the &lt;strong&gt;Containers&lt;/strong&gt; feature if you haven't done that yet. A reboot is required for this to add this feature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From now on you can easily switch with the menu item in the tray icon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There also is a command line tool to switch the engine. In a PowerShell windows you can type&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;amp; 'C:\Program Files\Docker\Docker\DockerCli.exe' -SwitchDaemon
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and it switches from Linux to Windows or vice versa. Take care and type the option as shown here as the option is case sensitive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="proxyfortherescue"&gt;Proxy for the rescue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But how does the switching work without the need to use another named pipe or socket from the Docker client?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer is that there is running a Proxy process &lt;code&gt;com.docker.proxy.exe&lt;/code&gt; which listens on the default named pipe &lt;code&gt;//./pipe/docker_engine&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you switch from Linux to Windows the Windows Docker engine &lt;code&gt;dockerd.exe&lt;/code&gt; will be started for you which is listening on another named pipe &lt;code&gt;//./pipe/docker_engine_windows&lt;/code&gt; and a new started Proxy process redirects to this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="underthehood"&gt;Under the hood&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have installed the &lt;a href="https://technet.microsoft.com/sysinternals/bb896645"&gt;Sysinternals Process Monitor&lt;/a&gt; tool to learn what happens while switching from Linux to Windows containers. With the Process Tree function you can see a timeline with green bars when each process has started or exited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following screenshot shows the processes before and after the switch. I have switched about in the middle of the green bar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2016/09/switch-to-windows-dockerd.png" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current &lt;code&gt;com.docker.proxy.exe&lt;/code&gt; (above &lt;code&gt;dockerd.exe&lt;/code&gt; in the list) that talked to the MobyLinuxVM exits as the dark green bar highlights that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;dockerd.exe&lt;/code&gt; Windows Docker engine is started, as well as a new &lt;code&gt;com.docker.proxy.exe&lt;/code&gt; (below &lt;code&gt;dockerd.exe&lt;/code&gt;) which talks to the Windows Docker engine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So just after the switch you still can use the &lt;code&gt;docker.exe&lt;/code&gt; Client or your Docker integration in your favorite editor or IDE without any environment changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="runningbothcontainerworldsinparallel"&gt;Running both container worlds in parallel&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The proxy process just switches the connection to the Docker engine. After such a switch both the Linux and Windows Docker engine are running.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="runalinuxwebserver"&gt;Run a Linux web server&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To try this out we first switch back to the Linux containers. Now we run the default nginx web server on port 80&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;docker run -p 80:80 -d nginx
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;then switch to the Windows containers with&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;amp; 'C:\Program Files\Docker\Docker\DockerCli.exe' -SwitchDaemon
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2016/09/docker-run-nginx.png" alt="docker-run-nginx"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let's run some Windows containers. But first we try if the Linux container is still running and reachable with&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;start http://localhost
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the &lt;code&gt;start&lt;/code&gt; command you open Edge with the welcome page of the nginx running in a Linux container&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2016/09/nginx.png" alt="nginx"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, the Linux container is still running.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="buildawindowswebserver"&gt;Build a Windows web server&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Windows 10 you &lt;s&gt;only can run Nanoserver containers. There is no IIS docker image for Nanoserver&lt;/s&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;Ignite update&lt;/strong&gt;: You can run Nanoserver &lt;strong&gt;AND&lt;/strong&gt; windowsservercore containers on Windows 10.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But to demo how simple nanoserver containers could be I'll keep the following sample as it is. So we create our own small Node.js web server. First we write the simple web server app&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;notepad app.js
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enter this code as the mini web server in the file &lt;code&gt;app.js&lt;/code&gt; and save the file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-javascript"&gt;var http = require('http');
var port = 81;

function handleRequest(req, res) {
  res.end('Hello from Windows container, path = ' + req.url);
}

var server = http.createServer(handleRequest);

server.listen(port);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we build a Windows Docker image with that application. We open another editor to create the &lt;code&gt;Dockerfile&lt;/code&gt; with this command&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;notepad Dockerfile.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enter this as the &lt;code&gt;Dockerfile&lt;/code&gt;. As you can see only the &lt;code&gt;FROM&lt;/code&gt; line is different from a typical Linux Dockerfile. This one uses a Windows base image from the Docker Hub.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-Dockerfile"&gt;FROM stefanscherer/node-windows:6.7.0-nano

COPY app.js app.js

CMD [ &amp;quot;node&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;app.js&amp;quot; ]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Save the file and build the Docker image with the usual command&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;docker build -t webserver .
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Run the Windows web server as a Docker container with&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;docker run -p 81:81 -d webserver
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2016/09/docker-run-webserver-1.png" alt="docker-run-webserver"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the moment you can't connect directly with 127.0.0.1 to the container. But it is possible to use the IP address of the container. We need the ID or name of the container, so list the containers running with&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;docker ps
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then open the browser with the container's IP address:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;start http://$(docker inspect -f &amp;quot;{{ .NetworkSettings.Networks.nat.IPAddress }}&amp;quot; grave_thompson):81
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2016/09/docker-inspect.png" alt="docker-inspect"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally the port forwarding from the host to the container allows you to contact the web server on port 81 from another machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2016/09/curl-to-windows-10.png" alt="curl-to-windows-10"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yes, the Windows container is also handling requests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new Docker for Windows beta combines the two container worlds and simplifies building Docker images for both Linux and Windows, making a Windows 10 machine a good development platform for both.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And with a little awareness when to switch to the right Docker engine, both Linux and Windows containers can run side-by-side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please leave a comment if you have questions or improvements or want to share your thoughts. You can follow me on Twitter &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/stefscherer"&gt;@stefscherer&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss></html>