<!DOCTYPE html>
<html><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0"><channel><title>DockerCon - Stefan Scherer's Blog</title><description>Just my techie notes.</description><link>http://localhost:2368/</link><image><url>http://localhost:2368/favicon.png</url><title>DockerCon - Stefan Scherer's Blog</title><link>http://localhost:2368/</link></image><generator>Ghost 1.8</generator><lastBuildDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2018 21:36:22 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:2368/tag/dockercon/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title>DockerCon: LCOW and Windows Server 1709</title><description>&lt;div class="kg-card-markdown"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last week was a busy week as a Docker Captain. Many of us came to Copenhagen to DockerCon EU 2017. You may have heard of the surprising news about Kubernetes coming to Docker. But there were also some other new announcements about Windows Containers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="dockeronwindowsworkshop"&gt;Docker on Windows Workshop&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Monday&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/dockercon-lcow-and-windows-server-1709/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">59f3b65cdd4c1b0001e301e7</guid><category>DockerCon</category><category>windows-containers</category><category>LCOW</category><category>Windows Server 1709</category><dc:creator>Stefan Scherer</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 28 Oct 2017 00:18:11 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;div class="kg-card-markdown"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last week was a busy week as a Docker Captain. Many of us came to Copenhagen to DockerCon EU 2017. You may have heard of the surprising news about Kubernetes coming to Docker. But there were also some other new announcements about Windows Containers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="dockeronwindowsworkshop"&gt;Docker on Windows Workshop&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Monday I helped &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/EltonStoneman"&gt;Elton Stoneman&lt;/a&gt; in his Docker on Windows Workshop. This time it was a full-day workshop and it was fully packed with 50 people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2017/10/dowws.jpg" alt="Docker on Windows Workshop"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elton is always running the workshop at a rapic pace, but don't worry the workshop material is all public &lt;a href="https://github.com/sixeyed/docker-windows-workshop"&gt;available on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;. So we went through dockerizing &lt;a href="http://ASP.NET"&gt;ASP.NET&lt;/a&gt; apps, adding Prometheus, Grafana and an ELK stack for monitoring, building a Jenkins CI pipeline and finally running a Docker Swarm. There is lots of things to look up in the material. If you prefer a book, I can recommend his &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.de/Docker-Windows-Elt%E2%80%A6"&gt;Docker on Windows&lt;/a&gt; book which is also fully packed with many tips and tricks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="lcowtheinsidestory"&gt;LCOW - The Inside Story&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my favorite talks was by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/gigastarks"&gt;John Starks&lt;/a&gt; from Microsoft about Linux Container on Windows - The Inside Story. He explained how LinuxKit is used to run a small HyperV VM for the Linux containers to provide the Linux kernel. On his Windows 10 1709 machine he also gave pretty good live demos. The &lt;a href="https://dockercon.docker.com/watch/U7Bxp66uKmemZssjCTyXkm"&gt;video is online&lt;/a&gt; and is worth watching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2017/10/dcon-lcow.jpg" alt="Linux and Windows containers side-by-side"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the photo you can see an alpine and nanoserver container running side-by-side. So you will no longer need to switch between Linux and Windows containers, it just works. He also showed that volumes work between Linux and Windows containers. This demo was done with a special Docker engine as not all pull requests haven't been merged. But still challenging for me to try this on a own machine ...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="windowsserver1709"&gt;Windows Server 1709&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the DockerCon week Microsoft has announced the availability of Windows Server Version 1709 for download. I first looked at the Azure Portal, but found nothing yet. I also couldn't find the downloads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So after the LCOW talk I used a Windows 10 VM in Azure and installed the Fall Creators Update to have 1709 on that desktop machine. I found the missing pull request and compiled a Docker engine from source and then I had my LCOW moment:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2017/10/docker-run-lcow.gif" alt="docker-run-lcow"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you see this the first time working and know what technical details had to be solved make make it look so simple and easy - awesome!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next day I found the Windows Server 1709 ISO in my MSDN subscription. So I could start working on a Packer template in my &lt;a href="https://github.com/StefanScherer/packer-windows"&gt;packer-windows&lt;/a&gt; GitHub repo to automate the creation of such Windows VM's. But DockerCon is to meet people and learn new things: &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/NicholasDille"&gt;Nicholas Dille&lt;/a&gt; went another very interesting way to &lt;a href="http://dille.name/blog/2017/10/25/building-a-windowscontainer-docker-host-without-running-windows-setup/"&gt;build a VM with Docker without running Windows Setup&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="smallerwindowsimages"&gt;Smaller Windows images&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the last months we could follow the progress of the Windows Server in several Insider builds. I blogged about the &lt;a href="https://stefanscherer.github.io/exploring-new-nanoserver-insider-images/"&gt;smaller NanoServer Insider images&lt;/a&gt; in July going down to 80-90 MByte. Now with the new release of Windows Server 1709 and Windows 10 version 1709 we now can use official images.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;microsoft/windowsservercore:1709&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;microsoft/nanoserver:1709&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;microsoft/dotnet:2.0.0-*-nanoserver-1709&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;microsoft/aspnet:4.7.1-windowsservercore-1709&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest discussion is about having no PowerShell in the small nanoserver image. For me it's a nice fit to just &lt;code&gt;COPY&lt;/code&gt; deploy microservices into the Windows image.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven't seen an official PowerShell base image based on nanoserver, but there is at least the beta version&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;microsoft/powershell:6.0.0-beta.9-nanoserver-1709&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also have pushed some images to the Docker Hub to get started with other languages and tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2017/10/Bildschirmfoto-2017-10-19-um-11.14.43.png" alt="Bildschirmfoto-2017-10-19-um-11.14.43"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don't have HyperV installed in Windows Server 1709 (maybe you are running a VM in the Cloud) then you cannot run older Windows Docker image on the new server. All images have to be built based on the new 1709 base images.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Windows 10 users always use HyperV to run Linux or Windows containers, so you don't feel that hard constraint on your developer machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It will be interesting to see how the multiple Windows versions evolve and when the next Insider program is giving us early access to the upcoming features.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="captainshackday"&gt;Captains Hack Day&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On our Docker Captains Hack Day &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/mikesir87"&gt;Michael Irwin&lt;/a&gt; has started a better &lt;a href="https://github.com/mikesir87/swarm-viz"&gt;Swarm Visualizer 2.0&lt;/a&gt;. During the day we have added a first CI pipeline and - of course - Windows support. But not only Windows! With some magic multi-stage multi-arch builds we also managed to cross-build the visualizer on an Intel machine and create a Docker image for IBM z390 mainframes. &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/estesp"&gt;Phil Estes&lt;/a&gt; tested the image in the IBM cloud. I'll write a more detailed blog post about how to cross-build Node.js apps with Docker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2017/10/captain-hack-day.jpg" alt="captain-hack-day"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That was a fascinating week at DockerCon. Thanks to Jenny, Ashlinn, Victor, Mano ... for making this event so wonderful. I had a lot of hallway tracks to talk with many people about Windows Containers in devolpment and production. Share and learn!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stefan&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/stefscherer"&gt;@stefscherer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>7 Reasons to attend DockerCon</title><description>&lt;div class="kg-card-markdown"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I'm more than happy that I can make it to DockerCon in Austin, Texas. It is only a few weeks until the workshops and conference starts April, 17th. If you still need some good reasons why you should attend I can give you some ideas. And you will get 10%&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/7-reasons-to-attend-dockercon/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5986d4ec688a490001540972</guid><category>DockerCon</category><category>Docker</category><category>ARM</category><category>windows-containers</category><dc:creator>Stefan Scherer</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 29 Mar 2017 22:43:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;div class="kg-card-markdown"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I'm more than happy that I can make it to DockerCon in Austin, Texas. It is only a few weeks until the workshops and conference starts April, 17th. If you still need some good reasons why you should attend I can give you some ideas. And you will get 10% discount with the code &lt;strong&gt;CaptainStefan&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="workshops"&gt;Workshops&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Monday I'll be at the workshop &lt;strong&gt;Modernizing monolithic &lt;a href="http://ASP.NET"&gt;ASP.NET&lt;/a&gt; applications with Docker&lt;/strong&gt; where you can get some hands-on experience with Windows containers. You cannot have a better place if you want to get started with Docker on Windows. Michael Friis and Elton Stoneman from Docker and myself can answer all your questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="seesomedockerswarmdemos"&gt;See some Docker Swarm demos&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Come to the Community Theater on Tuesday, Apr 18th, 1:00 PM to see my live demo &lt;a href="https://dockercon.smarteventscloud.com/connect/sessionDetail.ww?SESSION_ID=109712"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Swarm 2 Go&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and how our team at SEAL Systems has built a portable multi-arch data center with Raspberry Pi and UP boards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2017/03/picloud.jpg" alt="picloud"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will have the chance to play the chaos monkey and unplug cables to see Docker swarm mode in action. With the help of LED's we can visualise failures and how Docker swarm gets healthy again. All steps to build such a cluster is available in an &lt;a href="https://github.com/sealsystems/tiny-cloud"&gt;open source repo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="learnaboutdockeronwindows"&gt;Learn about Docker on Windows&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Docker is no longer a thing only on Linux. There are several talks about Docker on the Windows platform that I want to see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://dockercon.smarteventscloud.com/connect/sessionDetail.ww?SESSION_ID=107846"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Docker for .NET developers&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; with Michele Leroux Bustamante, CIO, Solliance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://dockercon.smarteventscloud.com/connect/sessionDetail.ww?SESSION_ID=107848"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Escape your VMs with Image2Docker&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; with Elton Stoneman from Docker and Docker Captain Jeff Nickoloff&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://dockercon.smarteventscloud.com/connect/sessionDetail.ww?SESSION_ID=109233"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Beyond \ - the path to Windows and Linux parity in Docker&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; with Taylor Brown, Principal Lead Program Manager, Microsoft&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://dockercon.smarteventscloud.com/connect/sessionDetail.ww?SESSION_ID=106041"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Creating Effective Images&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; with Abby Fuller, Technical Evangelist, AWS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I also recommend to visit the Microsoft booth to hopefully see some Docker swarm mode on Windows Servers. I really look forward to see the latest news and talking with some of the Microsoft Container and Networking team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="multipleplatforms"&gt;Multiple platforms&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you think Docker is only Linux on Intel machines, then comparing it to an instrument it may look like this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2017/03/keyboard-535254_1920.jpg" alt="keyboard"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But as you can see the talks above, Docker is available on multiple platforms: Linux, Windows, from small ARM devices like the Raspberry Pi to big IBM machines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the whole spectrum of Docker more looks like this, and once you learned the Docker commands you are able to play this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2017/03/pipe-organ-669589_1920.jpg" alt="organ"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it is time to learn how easy it is to deploy your applications for more than one platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://dockercon.smarteventscloud.com/connect/sessionDetail.ww?SESSION_ID=106642"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;From Arm to Z: Building, Shipping, and Running a Multi-platform Docker Swarm&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; with Christopher Jones and Christy Perez from IBM&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See you at DockerCon! Ping me on Twitter &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/stefscherer"&gt;@stefscherer&lt;/a&gt; or with the DockerCon app to get in touch with me during that conference week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Adding Hyper-V support to 2016 TP5 Docker VM</title><description>&lt;div class="kg-card-markdown"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Back in June I have attended the &lt;a href="http://2016.dockercon.com"&gt;DockerCon&lt;/a&gt; in Seattle. Beside lots of new features in Docker 1.12 we heard about &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=A7ABdUmen9s"&gt;Windows Server and Docker&lt;/a&gt; and upcoming features in the Windows Docker engine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another highlight for me after the conference was a visit at the Microsoft Campus in Redmond&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/adding-hyper-v-support-to-2016-tp5-docker-vm/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5986d4ec688a490001540969</guid><category>Packer</category><category>Vagrant</category><category>Docker</category><category>Windows</category><category>Hyper-V</category><category>DockerCon</category><dc:creator>Stefan Scherer</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 04 Aug 2016 19:59:37 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;div class="kg-card-markdown"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Back in June I have attended the &lt;a href="http://2016.dockercon.com"&gt;DockerCon&lt;/a&gt; in Seattle. Beside lots of new features in Docker 1.12 we heard about &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=A7ABdUmen9s"&gt;Windows Server and Docker&lt;/a&gt; and upcoming features in the Windows Docker engine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another highlight for me after the conference was a visit at the Microsoft Campus in Redmond to meet the Windows Container team around Taylor Brown. After a meeting and having lunch we talked about making my Packer template for a &lt;a href="https://github.com/StefanScherer/packer-windows/blob/my/windows_2016_docker.json"&gt;Windows Server 2016 TP5 Docker VM&lt;/a&gt; work with Hyper-V. At that time my packer template supported only VirtualBox and VMware with a &lt;a href="https://stefanscherer.github.io/setup-local-windows-2016-tp5-docker-vm/"&gt;blog post describing how to build it&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2016/08/20160623_101541.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So Patrick Lang from Microsoft and I started to have a look at the pull request &lt;a href="https://github.com/mitchellh/packer/pull/2576"&gt;mitchellh/packer#2576&lt;/a&gt; by Taliesin Sisson that adds a Hyper-V builder to Packer. After a couple of days (already back to Germany working in different time zones) we improved the template through &lt;a href="https://github.com/PatrickLang/packer-windows/commit/7e13d4799e28a3afb1e35b878e00394256011022"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; and finally got it working.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="packerbuildvagrantup"&gt;packer build, vagrant up&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you haven't heard about &lt;a href="https://www.packer.io"&gt;Packer&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.vagrantup.com"&gt;Vagrant&lt;/a&gt; let me explain it with the following diagram. If you want to create a VM from an ISO file you normally click through your hypervisor UI and then follow the installation steps inside the VM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2016/08/packer_vagrant.png" alt="packer build, vagrant up"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With Packer you can automate that step building a VM from an ISO file, put all steps into a Packer template and then just share the template so others can just run&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;packer build template.json
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our case the output is a Vagrant box. That is a compressed VM ready to be used with the next tool - Vagrant. It takes a Vagrant box, creates a copy of it to turn it on so you can work again and again with the same predefined VM that was built by Packer. You want to turn your VM on? Just type&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;vagrant up
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You want to stop the VM after work? Just type&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;vagrant halt
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You want to try something out and want to undo all that to start over with the clean state. Just destroy it and start it again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;vagrant destroy
vagrant up
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are much more commands and even snapshots can be used. The advantage is that you don't have to know all the buttons in your hypervisor. Both Packer and Vagrant are available for &lt;strong&gt;Windows, Mac and Linux&lt;/strong&gt; and also &lt;strong&gt;support &lt;a href="http://www.slideshare.net/PuppetLabs/multiprovider-vagrant"&gt;multiple hypervisors&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and even cloud providers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So you only have to learn one or both of these tools and you're done if you have to work with VM's.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="addinghypervbuilder"&gt;Adding Hyper-V builder&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Packer template for a VM has one or more builder sections. The Hyper-V section looks like this and contains the typical steps&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adding files for a virtual floppy for the first boot&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Defining disk size, memory and CPU's&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to login into the VM&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-json"&gt;    {
      &amp;quot;vm_name&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;WindowsServer2016TP5Docker&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;type&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;hyperv-iso&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;disk_size&amp;quot;: 41440,
      &amp;quot;boot_wait&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;0s&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;headless&amp;quot;: false,
      &amp;quot;guest_additions_mode&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;disable&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;iso_url&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;{{user `iso_url`}}&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;iso_checksum_type&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;{{user `iso_checksum_type`}}&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;iso_checksum&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;{{user `iso_checksum`}}&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;floppy_files&amp;quot;: [
        &amp;quot;./answer_files/2016/Autounattend.xml&amp;quot;,
        &amp;quot;./floppy/WindowsPowershell.lnk&amp;quot;,
        &amp;quot;./floppy/PinTo10.exe&amp;quot;,
        &amp;quot;./scripts/disable-winrm.ps1&amp;quot;,
        &amp;quot;./scripts/docker/enable-winrm.ps1&amp;quot;,
        &amp;quot;./scripts/microsoft-updates.bat&amp;quot;,
        &amp;quot;./scripts/win-updates.ps1&amp;quot;
      ],
      &amp;quot;communicator&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;winrm&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;winrm_username&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;vagrant&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;winrm_password&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;vagrant&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;winrm_timeout&amp;quot; : &amp;quot;4h&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;shutdown_command&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;shutdown /s /t 10 /f /d p:4:1 /c \&amp;quot;Packer Shutdown\&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;ram_size_mb&amp;quot;: 2048,
      &amp;quot;cpu&amp;quot;: 2,
      &amp;quot;switch_name&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;{{user `hyperv_switchname`}}&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;enable_secure_boot&amp;quot;:true
    },
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Packer can also download ISO files from a download link to make automation very easy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The installation of a Windows Server 2016 VM can be automated with an &lt;a href="https://github.com/StefanScherer/packer-windows/blob/my/answer_files/2016/Autounattend.xml"&gt;&lt;code&gt;Autounattend.xml&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; file. This file contains information to setup the Windows VM until the WinRM service is up and running and Packer can login from the host machine to run further provision scripts to setup the VM with additional installations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In case of the Windows Server 2016 TP5 Docker VM we additionally &lt;a href="https://github.com/StefanScherer/packer-windows/blob/my/scripts/docker/install-docker.ps1"&gt;install Docker 1.12&lt;/a&gt; and pull the Windows base OS docker images into the VM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All these steps defined in the Packer template build a good Vagrant box to have Docker preinstalled with the base docker image as it takes some time to download it the first time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So after a &lt;code&gt;vagrant destroy&lt;/code&gt; you still have the Windows OS docker images installed and can work with a clean installation again. Only from time to time when there is a new OS docker image version you have to rebuild your Vagrant box with Packer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="buildthehypervvagrantbox"&gt;Build the Hyper-V Vagrant box&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To build the Vagrant box locally on a Windows 10 machine you only need the &lt;strong&gt;Hyper-V feature&lt;/strong&gt; activated and you need a &lt;strong&gt;special version of &lt;code&gt;packer.exe&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; (notice: with &lt;code&gt;choco install packer&lt;/code&gt; you only get the upstream packer where the hyperv builder is not integrated yet). The packer.exe with hyperv builder can be downloaded at &lt;a href="https://dl.bintray.com/taliesins/Packer/"&gt;https://dl.bintray.com/taliesins/Packer/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clone my packer template from GitHub and build it with these commands:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;git clone https://github.com/StefanScherer/packer-windows
cd packer-windows
packer build --only=hyperv-iso windows_2016_docker.json
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will take some time downloading and caching the ISO file, booting, installing the software and pulling the first Docker images.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sharevagrantboxeswithatlas"&gt;Share Vagrant boxes with Atlas&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another advantage of Vagrant is that you can share Vagrant base boxes through Atlas, a service by HashiCorp. So only one has to run Packer and build the Vagrant box and provide it for other team members or the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2016/08/packer_vagrant_atlas.png" alt="packer atlas vagrant"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Others can create a &lt;code&gt;Vagrantfile&lt;/code&gt; with the box name of one of the provided Vagrant boxes. That name will be used at the first &lt;code&gt;vagrant up&lt;/code&gt; to download the correct Vagrant box for the hypervisor to be used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even Microsoft has its first &lt;a href="https://atlas.hashicorp.com/Microsoft/boxes/EdgeOnWindows10"&gt;Vagrant box at Atlas&lt;/a&gt; which can be used with VirtualBox only at the moment. But it is only a matter of time that more Hyper-V based Vagrant boxes will show up in Atlas, also boxes for other hypervisors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don't have a Vagrantfile you even can create a simple one to start a new test environment with two commands and a suitable Vagrant box from Atlas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;vagrant init Microsoft/EdgeOnWindows10
vagrant up --provider virtualbox
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vagrant itself can log into the VM through WinRM and run further provision scripts to setup a good development or test environment. It is just a decision what to install in a Vagrant box with Packer and what to install with Vagrant afterwards. You decide which flexibility you want or if you prefer a faster &lt;code&gt;vagrant up&lt;/code&gt; experience with a full provisioned Vagrant box that was built with a longer running Packer build once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="dockerwindowsbox"&gt;docker-windows-box&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are looking for a test environment for Windows Docker containers you might have a look at my &lt;a href="https://github.com/StefanScherer/docker-windows-box"&gt;docker-windows-box&lt;/a&gt; GitHub repo that installs Git and some additional Docker tools to get started working on some &lt;a href="https://github.com/StefanScherer/dockerfiles-windows"&gt;Windows Dockerfiles&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2016/08/docker-windows-box.png" alt="docker windows box"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm happy that there is a Hyper-V builder for Packer that really works. Vagrant already has a Hyper-V provider built in so you can have the same experience running and working with VM's as others have with VMware or VirtualBox.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With a such a TP5 Vagrant box it is very easy to get in touch with Windows Docker Containers, regardless if you are working on Windows 10 with Hyper-V or from your Mac or Linux machine with another hypervisor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2016/08/packer_multiprovider.png" alt="Packer multiprovider"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please leave a comment if you have questions or improvements or want to share your thoughts. You can follow me on Twitter &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/stefscherer"&gt;@stefscherer&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss></html>